(サクラ)ナルト！ どこ行くの!?
Naruto! Where are you going?!
エロ仙人が
五代目火影になってたら➡
If Pervy Sage had been
the Fifth Hokage...
綱手のばあちゃんに
こんなムチャはさせなかった。
he wouldn't have let Granny Tsunade
take such risks...
ぜってえ…。
Never!
ナルト！
サクラ いい。
Naruto!
Sakura... It's all right.
Let him be.
少し そっとしておいてやれ。
でも…。
But...
あの子が自来也ちゃんを
まっすぐに慕っとったのが➡
I can see that child truly loved
and admired Jiraiya-chan.
ようわかった。
予言の子は
あの子であってほしいと➡
I can't help but hope that
he is the Child of Prophecy.
そう願わずにはおれんの。
i realise the screaming pain
hearing loud in my brain
but i'm going straight ahead with the scar
I should just get over it and I should just stop feeling it
wasurete shimaeba ii yo kanjinaku nacchaeba ii
and so I covered my grazed heart
surimuita kokoro ni futa wo shitan da
I don't care if I'm hurt 'cause I don't feel pain anymore
kizutsuitatte heki da yo mou itami wa nai kara ne
all while you limped on while dragging your feet behind you
sono ashi wo hikizuri nagara mo
I had lost sight of myself
miushinatta jibun jishin ga
which had crumbled loudly to the ground
oto wo taete kuzureteita
but then I realised it was just the sound of the wind...
kizukeba kaze no oto dake ga
I came here to tell you something following my deep scars
tsutae ni kita yo kizuato wo tadotte
before I am completely crushed by this vast world
sekai ni oshitsubusarete shimau mae ni
do you remember that sky of tears
oboeteru kana namida no sora wo
that pain protected you for me
ano itami ga kimi no koto wo mamotte kureta
that pain is always protecting you
sono itami ga itsumo kimi wo mamotterunda
can you hear me so am i
Following the Master's Shadow
((悪いな
いつも損な役回りを押し付けて。
I'm sorry... that you always get
the short end of the stick.
ハハハ！ なんだ急に!?
What's with you?!
火影になるべきは
本来 お前だったということだ。
I'm saying, you were supposed
to be Hokage.
三代目は
ずっと次の火影を お前にと…。
The Third always wanted
you to be the next to--
ワシは そんなガラじゃあない。
自由気ままが性に…。
I was never cut out for
that sort of thing.
Being on my own suits me too well...
大蛇丸を
止められなかったことを悔い➡
You regretted not being able
to stop Orochimaru.
ずっと 大蛇丸の動きを
１人で調べ回っていたのだろう？
So all that time,
you were tracking his movements
alone, isn't that right?
フッ… もう その必要もなくなった。
I no longer need to do so.
(これで小説の続編も
早く出せるってもんだ))
That means I get to release
the sequel to my novel sooner.
(フカサク)綱手ちゃん！
Tsunade-chan...
Tsunade-chan!
あの… 大丈夫ですか？ 師匠。
Are you all right, Master?
あぁ 問題ない。
申し訳ありません。
Yes, I'm fine.
I'm sorry.
報せを聞いたばかりじゃ。
気落ちするのもムリはないがの➡
You just received sad news.
I don't blame you
for feeling distraught.
じゃけん おぬしには
里を守るゆう大事な仕事がある。
However, you have the important duty
of protecting the village.
今が踏ん張りどきじゃ。
はい。
This is where you must stay strong.
それで 自来也ちゃんが残した
手がかりについてじゃが➡
Yes...
Anyway, the clues left by Jiraiya-chan...
実は この背中の暗号以外にも
預かっているものがあっての。
There is something besides
the hidden message on my back.
コヤツの腹の中には
自来也ちゃんが拘束した➡
A Hidden Rain Ninja captured by
Jiraiya-chan is inside his belly.
雨隠れの忍が入っとる。
そして もう１つ… フンッ！
And, one more thing...
コヤツの中には
１体だけ倒すことに成功した➡
Inside this fellow is one of Pain's bodies
that Jiraiya managed to kill.
ペインの死体が。
ペインの!?
Pain's?
"MAKE-OUT TACTICS"
LONG-AWAITED NEW NOVEL BEST WORK EVER
((グググ… おぉ おるおる！
Oh, there they are!
ピッチピチのギャルちゃんたちが！
So many well-developed gals!
こら！ 何やってんだ エロ仙人！
Hey! What're you doing, Pervy Sage!
(眼福 眼福！
次回作への意欲が湧くの。 グフフ))
What a sight! What a sight!
I'm getting inspiration
for my next novel!
"Autopsy Room"
(フカサク)これが ペインじゃ。
This is Pain...
(シズネ)
波紋模様… 伝説の輪廻眼ですか。
The ripple pattern...
Is it the legendary Rinnegan?
(フカサク)そうじゃ 詳しく調べれば➡
That's correct. If we study it well,
アヤツらを倒すヒントが
見えてくるかもしれん。
we may find clues on how
to defeat him.
忍の体は情報の宝庫。
何よりの手がかりです。
A ninja's corpse is
a treasure trove of information.
選りすぐりの医忍を集め
早急に検死を始めます。
We will gather skilled Medical Ninja,
and begin an autopsy immediately.
シズネ。
はい お任せください。
Shizune.
Yes, ma'am. I will take care of it.
ふむ… よう撮れとるわい。
Hmm... That is a good photo.
これで 預かったものは
すべて渡したぞ。
I have given you all that
was entrusted to me.
えぇ たしかに。
Yes, indeed.
ワシは帰るが
何かわかったら知らせてくれ。
I will return home now.
Let me know what you learn.
自来也ちゃんの弟子がいれば➡
With Jiraiya-chan's student here,
妙木山とも
連絡がつくじゃろうからな。
you will be able to
contact Mount Myoboku.
ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
必ずや ペイン攻略の手がかりを
つかんでみせます！
I promise that we will find
a way to defeat Pain!
((自来也 : いいか ナルト。
Now listen, Naruto.
お前を強くするのに使える時間は
たった３年だ。
I have only three years to
make you strong.
その間 ビッシビシ鍛えてやるから
覚悟しろのぉ。
I will spend that time
training you vigorously.
Be prepared for that.
もちろんだってばよ！ オレは
今度こそ アイツを連れ戻すんだ！
You bet! This time, I'm going to
bring him back for sure!
立ち止まってる暇なんかねえ！
There's no time for me to waste.
もう我慢できねえ！
Cripes... I can't stand this...
何なんだってばよ
この地味な修業は！
What is this?!
What's with this lame training?!
バカモン！ 修業に地味も派手もあるか
このバカ弟子が!!
Fool! Nothing in training is lame!
You foolish student!
うぉ～!!
もらった！
You're mine!
ハハハハ！ 影分身を使えるのは
お前だけじゃないぞ。
You're not the only one
who uses Shadow Clones.
まだまだ甘いのぉ。
You're still so naïve...
あぁ… クソッ！
惜しかったってばよ。
Damn! I was so close!
ウソつけ！ お前がワシに勝とうなんざ
100年早いのぉ。
Liar. It'll take a hundred years
before you can beat me.
100年も待てるかっての。
見てろよ 今度こそ…。
I can't wait a hundred years!
Just wait... Next time...
これ 超かっこいいってばよ！
This is super-cool!
(ほう 馬子にも衣装って
ヤツかのぉ？))
Hmm... Fine feathers make
a fine bird, eh?
(イルカ)よっ ナルト！
Yo! Naruto.
任務でも ずいぶん
活躍してるみたいだな。
I hear you've been real active
on missions and such.
里のみんなも ウワサしてるぞ。
Everyone in the village
is talking about you.
久しぶりに
話でもしないか？
Hey, let's go somewhere and catch up!
一楽でも行くか？ ラーメン！
How about Ichiraku for some ramen?
やめとく…。
No thanks...
(シカマル)え？ 今からっすか？
What? Right now?
そうだ。 それを持って
今すぐ行ってこい。
Yes. Take that,
and go immediately.
暗号解読班のヤツらって➡
The Cipher Corps folks
don't work this late.
こんな時間まで
仕事してないっすけど。
私の命令だといって 召集しろ。
Summon them and tell them
it's on my orders.
とにかく この件は お前に任せた。
I'm putting you in charge of this case.
重要な暗号ってことは
わかってますけど➡
I know it's a very important encryption,
他に任務のない
ヒマなヤツとか誰かに…。
but can't you ask someone else
who's not on a mission right now?
ちょっ… どこ行くんすか？
Wait... Where are you going?
オレは もともと
別件で ここに…。
I came here on a different matter.
シカマル！
ん？
Shikamaru!
でもよ…。
今日は 綱手様➡
But...
Tsunade-sama has been busy
since morning, and...
朝から ずっと
忙しくされていたから。
そりゃあ こっちだって…。
シカマル お願い。
Well, the same goes for me.
Shikamaru, please...
((しかし… お前
また きれいになったのぉ。
I must say...
You've grown even more beautiful.
(相変わらずだねぇ))
You haven't changed...
((もし その木ノ葉の里を➡
But... If you try anything to
betray the village...
裏切るようなマネをしてみろ。
(そのときは ワシがお前を殺すぞ))
At that moment, I will kill you.
((じゃあ お得意のギャンブルといこう。
Then how about making a bet with me?
お前は ワシの死ぬほうに賭けろ。
You bet that I will die.
After all, you always lose.
お前の賭けは
必ず外れるからのぉ。
そのかわり
ワシが生きて帰ってきたときは…。
But if I make it back alive...
アハハハハ！ 冗談だ 冗談！
Joking! I'm just joking!
お前には感謝してる。
You know, I'm grateful to you.
はじめましてだな。
オレ 自来也ってんだ。
Heya... I'm Jiraiya!
ラブレターは あとでいいぜ。
よろしく！
You can send me the love letters later!
Nice to meet ya!
(ヒヒヒ！))
バカ野郎…。
You fool...
"24-HOUR CONVENIENCE STORE"
(イルカ)ナルト…。
Naruto...
自来也様のことは聞いたよ。
I heard about Jiraiya-sama.
オレのこと… ずっと
見ててほしかった。
I wanted him to keep watching
over me.
オレが 火影になるとこ
見ててもらいたかったのに。
I wanted him to see me
become the Hokage.
エロ仙人には かっこわりいとこ
ばっかしか見せらんなくって…。
But I only ended up showing Pervy Sage
the worst, most un-cool side of me.
オレってば…。
I was...
自来也様は お前のことを
いつも褒めてたよ。
Jiraiya-sama only had praise for you.
自分の孫のようだと いつも
鼻高々に 話してくださった。
He was always boasting about you,
saying you were like
his own grandchild.
お前が 自分の意志を継ぐ存在だと
信じていた。
He had faith that you were
the one who would inherit his will.
いずれ 立派な火影になると
信じて疑ってなかった。
And truly believed that
you would one day become
a great Hokage.
自来也様は お前を
ずっと見てるさ。
Jiraiya-sama will always
watch over you.
今だって どこからかな。
Even this very minute,
he's watching from somewhere.
あの人は お前が落ち込んで
いるのを見ても➡
He wouldn't be happy
seeing you sad like this. So...
褒めてはくれないぞ。
だから 今までどおりの➡
Be your usual self,
the one he praised so much.
褒めてもらえるような
お前でいればいい。
いつまでも 落ち込んでんな。
Don't stay depressed forever.
お前は あの三忍 自来也様が
認めた…。
For Jiraiya-sama himself,
one of the Legendary Sannin...
優秀な弟子なんだからな。
acknowledged you as
his promising student!
ありがとう… イルカ先生。
Thanks... Iruka-sensei.
ん～っ！
お疲れです。 どうっすか？
Thank you for your efforts.
How's it going?
あぁ いろいろ調べてみたがね➡
Oh...
I checked very carefully...
これ 木ノ葉隠れの
暗号じゃないね。
But this isn't a Hidden Leaf code.
どのアルゴリズムにも 適応せんからね。
It doesn't correspond to any
of our algorithms.
自来也様が ギリギリで遺されたことを
考えると➡
But considering the fact
that Jiraiya-sama wrote this
in his dying moments,
それほど複雑な暗号ではないと
思うがね。
I don't think it could be
anything too complex.
数字の羅列だから
共通鍵暗号だね。
It's a string of numbers,
so it has to be
a shared-key encryption.
解読… できるんっすか？
Can you... decode it?
(シホ)オホンッ！
Ahem.
え～ ぶっちゃけ
鍵を知らないとムリです。
Err... Frankly, it's impossible
unless we know the key.
鍵？
Key?
つまり この暗号を解く
規則を知らなくては➡
Namely, if you don't know
the rules that define the code,
絶対に解けません はい。
you can't break it.
自来也様と共通の
何かしらの鍵となる➡
Unless we know something
about Jiraiya-sama
決め事を知らなければ ダメです。
that could be the key,
it's impossible.
じゃあ どうすれば その鍵を…？
So how do we figure out what the key is?
それは わかりませんが➡
I wouldn't know...
自来也様のことを
よく知っておられる方なら➡
But perhaps someone who
was close to Jiraiya-sama
鍵を知っておられるかも
しれませんね。
would recognize the key.
お亡くなりになった
状況からして➡
Although, given the circumstances
of his death,
遺した情報の内容を
敵に知られぬよう➡
the encryption could have
been hastily created
急きょ 思いつかれた
暗号かもしれんから➡
to prevent the enemy from
discerning his message.
なんとも言えんがね。
So we can't say for certain.
誰に伝えたかったのか考えて
その方にあたってみれば➡
Consider who he may have
intended that message for,
and ask that person.
And perhaps you'll find some clues.
何か
手掛かりがあるかもしれんね。
だとすると まずは 五代目か
カカシ先生か…。
Which means...
The Fifth or Kakashi-sensei...
んじゃ ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
また 何かあったら 伺いますんで。
If I learn anything new,
I'll come again.
あぁ でも 帰って寝てるから
家に来てね 家に。
Sure, but I'll be home in bed,
so just come by the house, ok?
さて 帰って寝ますかね。
Well... I'm heading home to sleep.
シホちゃんは？
What about you, Shiho-chan?
誰かが ここにいないと
いけませんから。
Someone's gotta stay behind.
(カカシ)９ 31 ８ 106 ７
207 15…。
9... 31... 8... 106... 7... 207... 15...
何か 思いつかないっすか？
Can you think of anything?
自来也様と交わした会話とかで
この数字に関すること。
Maybe in a conversation
with Jiraiya-sama?
Something about these numbers...?
ん？
この 106って数字は たしか…。
This number 106 is...
((自来也様？
106だの。
Jiraiya-sama?
It's 106.
何がですか？
What is?
(106センチ))
106 centimeters.
いや 違うな…。
No... That's not it.
オレには 何も思いつかないな。
I can't think of anything.
今度は 五代目か
ナルトにあたってみたらどうだ？
Why don't you try
the Fifth or Naruto next?
五代目のところには
もう行きました。
I already asked the Fifth.
はぁ… あとは ナルトっすか。
Which leaves Naruto...
暗号のこともそうだが
アイツのことも心配でね。
The secret code is a concern.
But I'm also worried about Naruto.
Try to cheer him up.
そっちのほうも頼む。
あんまり期待されてもね。
Don't get your hopes up too high.
なんだ 留守かよ。
Shoot... He's out.
シカマルか 何だってばよ。
Shikamaru... What do you want?
とりあえず あがっていいか？
For starters... Can I come in?
どうだ？ 何かわかったか？
Well? Can you think of anything?
おい ナルト！ どうなんだ!?
Hey Naruto, I said can you think
of anything?
ナルト！
Naruto!
あぁ わりい わりい
で 何だっけ？
Oh sorry. What was it again?
お前 ちょっとオレに付き合え。
Come with me.
どこ？
まぁ いいからよ。
Where?
Just come.
なんだってばよ。
Wh-What is it?!
"LEAF HOSPITAL"
なんだって急に こんなとこ…。
Why'd you bring me here?
ちょっと待っとけ。
Just wait.
おっ 来た！
Ah! Here she comes.
えっ!? 紅先生!?
あぁ。
Huh?! Kurenai-sensei...
焼き肉の食いすぎで病院かよ！
チョウジ以上じゃん 腹。
Yeah...
Were you hospitalized for
eating too much barbeque?!
Your stomach's bigger than Choji's!
お子さんだ 肉じゃねえ。
She's pregnant, not fat!
つうか 面倒くせえな
やっぱ お前は。
Cripes, you're still
as obnoxious as ever.
Huh?!
えっ じゃあ…。
You mean... she's...?
(紅)シカマル あなた
毎回 ここに来るのやめなさい。
Shikamaru, stop coming here so often.
そうも いかないっすよ
アスマに頼まれてるんすから。
Sorry, no can do.
Asuma asked me to do so.
シカマル アスマ先生に頼まれたって…。
Shikamaru... What did Asuma
ask you to do?
あの子は オレの弟子になる。
That child will be my student.
Huh?
アスマから託された子だ。
Asuma entrusted that child to me.
自来也様のことは聞いた。
I heard about Jiraiya-sama.
オレも師を亡くしてっから➡
I lost my teacher,
お前の気持が
わからないでもないけどよ。
so it's not like I don't understand
what you're going through.
ウジウジしてても始まらねえだろ。
But whining and sulking isn't going
to make things better.
とっくに そんな立場じゃ
なくなってんだよ。
We're way past that point in our lives.
どういうことだってばよ。
What do you mean?
オレは師から
いろいろなものを託された。
My teacher entrusted me
with many things.
重要なことから
くだらないことまで いろいろだ。
Some important, some petty.
All sorts of things.
お前だって そうだろう。
You too, right?
それこそ 数限りなくよ。
In fact, you must have a ton of stuff.
そろそろなんじゃねえか。
So don't you think it's about time
for us to step up?
オレたちも。
何が？
Time for what?
託される側から
託す側にならねえとよ。
Time for us to become
the ones who entrust.
面倒くせえけど
そうも言ってらんねえだろ。
It's a pain,
but we can't keep complaining.
お前も いずれ
ラーメンをおごる側になるし➡
You will eventually be
the one treating to ramen,
ナルト先生とか呼ばれるんだからよ。
and you'll be called Naruto-sensei,
or something.
オレたちだって いつまでも
ガキのままじゃいられねえ。
We can't stay brats forever...
アスマや自来也様みてえな➡
If we wanna become super cool ninja
like Asuma and Jiraiya-sama, that is.
あんな
かっけえ忍になりてえならよ。
そうだな サンキュー シカマル。
You're right.
Thanks, Shikamaru.
もっと しっかりしろよ。
Pull yourself together.
お前には
やることがあるんだからよ。
You got work to do.
おう！
Right!
here are the answers of the path
koko ni aru no wa kimi ga ima made erande michi no
you chose up till now, look and go on by yourself
kotae tachi yo hora jishin motte susumeba ii
it's very natural, like a rainbow over
totemo shizen na no amaeagari no
asphalt after a rainfall
asufaruto ni niji ga kakaru you ni
a lonely wind blew and
lonely kaze ga fuite
a feeling dawned on me
feeling ki ga tsuita yo
there's no answer anywhere
kotae wo doko ni mo nai kedo
call me, I got it already
call me wakatteru wa
with you, we'll always
with you ai wa itsu mo
love each other
atae au mono
for you
I'm sure one day you will
kitto kimi wa itsu no hi ka
be able to fly in the sky
kono sora wo toberu hazu dakara
no matter how many times we've stumbled for you
nando tsumaizuta to shite mo for you
there's only one thing important
taisetsu na koto wa hitotsu
which is to dream
yumemiru koto
so at least keep your heart open
kokoro dake wa tozasanaide ite
Next Episode
(ナツ)うお～りゃ!!
Comrades move on to decode the message left behind.
Entrusted to Naruto from Jiraiya, what is the key to the encryption?
Shikamaru's brain and Shiho's experience leads them
(ダン)フェイント 成功ぜよ！
to a certain answer.
おっ…。
Finally, the hidden mystery is revealed!
うわぁ！
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "Decryption"
まだまだ！
Decryption
What is Jiraiya's message?
やるぅ！ そうこなくっちゃ
おもしろくないぜよ！